so this is an excerpt from majima
41 householders there are three kinds of
bodily conduct not in accordance with
the dhama unrighteous conduct there are
four kinds of verbal conduct not in
accordance with the dhama uh and there
are three kinds of mental conduct not in
accordance with the dhama and how
householders are there three kinds of
poliy conduct not in accordance with the
dma uh it's
when somebody kills living beings when
somebody takes by way of theft the
wealth and property of others when he
misconducts himself in sensual
Pleasures meaning he
has uh improper sexual
relationships um then there are four
kinds of verbal conduct not not in
accordance with the dhama uh when
somebody Lies when
they when they speak
maliciously so as to divide groups
divide one group from the other group or
divide the other group from the first
group uh when one speaks
harshly and then when they speak
um basically useless talk or frivolous
talk and then there are three kinds of
mental conduct not in accordance with
the Dum the first one is
covetousness the second one is ill
will and the third one is wrong View and
here is the part of Interest it says or
he has wrong view distorted Vision thus
there is nothing given nothing offered
nothing sacrificed no fruit or result of
good and bad actions no this world no
other world world no mother no father no
beings who are reborn spontaneously no
good and virtuous recklessness and
Brahman in the world who have themselves
realized by direct knowledge and declare
this world and the other world those are
the three types of mental
misconduct so householders it is by
reason of such conduct not in accordance
with the
dhama um that some beings here on the
dissolution of of the body after death
reappear in states of deprivation
and unhappy destination in predition
even in
hell so basically
the it's uh something that people might
Overlook that wrong view is on the same level
that wrong view is on the same level
as these actions that person might have
overcome and you know just through basic
virtue and keeping the five precepts but
um
you know it sounds as a as like a very
coarse or crude kind of view like nobody
actually believes that it it sounds as
if um it's something that everybody
would have gone beyond just by becoming
a Buddhist for example but
uh that wrong
view is actually something that
is much more deeply rooted and much more
like basically if you fully abandoned
that view you would be a Sal upon so
there have there has to be traces of
that view in your experience even if you
don't uh outright tell others like no I
believe that there is nothing given or I
believe that there is no mother and no
father there is some trace of that in
you uh if you not assult upon us so then
that um so I thought we could explore
um so I thought we could explore
how
um yeah how would those views manifest
given that it's not the the obvious
intention to believe these things
so here we start with the beginning like
there's nothing given nothing offered
nothing sacrificed
um so why is that a wrong
View and what what does that mean
exactly does it mean to say
um is talking
about like
what what's what it's really saying is
it makes no difference whether you give
something to someone or not like it's
it's connected with the second Point
like there's no result of good and bad
action so basically just it makes no
difference you just go through
life um and it's kind of like random
like things that happen to you are are a
result of
just uh you know random things happening
the world Chaos Theory some Cosmic force
or other yeah and then
um it it it basically the reason why
that view is incompatible with the right
view is because I mean the most basic
point is just takes away the fact that
you are responsible for your own
suffering most important if you can't
accept is not just like uh the fact that
you won't be making Merit because if you
have that wrong view it's the fact that
it it blocks the understanding of the
dhma itself because then you like how
are you going to recognize that that uh
you yourself because good results is good
yourself because good results is good
and bad action doesn't just mean uh ver
bodily and verbal action as the Su
itself said it talks about mental action
as well so how will you purify yourself
if you don't believe that the actions
that you're doing have results it's just
the most basic thing yeah so that first
one is always enough um but
then what does it mean for example not
to believe that there is Mother and
Father
mhm well most generally things in the
world come with their own
significance and in terms of one's
relationship with human
beings um one's father and mother are um
they have a special
significance um and so it is important to recognize
um and so it is important to recognize
on the most General level things have
significance and even if there are
unpleasant aspects connected with that
um to to not um deny the significance
and just see everything as basically
equal like there is no father there is
no mother and just say well it's they
just all human beings and you can extend
that principle further and then in in
the wrong way start taking things apart
as if it almost doesn't exist that would
be a sort of continuation of that same
wrong view but the fact is that as an
infant you fully dependent on uh let's
say parents or caretakers generally and
without their support you simply
wouldn't have made it and there's
another discourse where Buddha in fact
indicates that it's not easy to repay
what one's parents have done and there
are some telling similes there as
well so to to see that um is part of of
that right view um so so then the
question is yeah do you have a say in
the significance that things have for
example that's a good question to ask in
this context like am I creating
the significance of things that I
encounter in my world or is that
something that I sort of find myself
in right yeah because uh it's not that
people want it's not that
um the problem basically is that you
would start denying naturally when you
try to overcome suffering the natural
direction is again as you said to start
denying the significance of things
because the significance of things is
Mis understood to be suffering or is
misunderstood to be greed of vision and
delusion so for example you would
confuse the fact the fact that there is
a special significance to your parents
as you said because they have raised you
and they have like it just doesn't
matter what you do for better or worse
even if you hate your parents it's
always going to have some sort of
special significance and so if you then
start thinking that you know being free
from craving for example means not to
that you know your parents don't matter
anymore because you have no attachment
you have no you have no concern for the
world you have abandoned all all concern
from the world then you would be
implicitly assuming like you would be
overshooting the mark and seeing Oh so I
have to also deny the significance of
these things yes in order to accomplish
freedom from suffering and then that
denial extends to very subtle um
attitudes like you know when people say
uh well everything is just constantly
changing none of this really exists um
or when they try to mix dama with
science like it's just the atoms and and
subatomic particles yeah or behaving the
way I do because of my genes or DNA
which I inherited for my parents so
really they are to blame which is sort
of an inverted significance almost yeah
or on top of the like oh there's there's
no mother it's just a collection of
atoms that I call mother like you could
I guess go the other way while
simultaneously doing the exact same
thing this might be for the maybe
intense meditator who's like oh you know
it's not actually a mother it's just a
collection of like visual data EXA you
know bare sense perceptions and uh yeah
even if you if you don't talk with with
scientific terms you say oh no no that's
just a perception that's just a sight
mhm and you might be like generally
trying to practice the dhama like
because the Buddha says see everything
is just you know in terms of the six and
spases of the five Aggregates but you're
going the wrong way you're using it to
basically essentially try to say there
is no mother and there's no father
because it's just a feeling it's just a
perception but that's on the wrong level
you have to say yes it is just a feeling
and just a perception that has a very
great significance like compared to the
other things but the point is that you
need to be
basically uh uh acknowledging that things have a
uh uh acknowledging that things have a
certain significance and
then within that basis you you know
develop the practice not like take a
shortcut basically so you want to
uncover things rather than kind of cover
things up ideas of yeah you you un you
you let
it you let it be with what it is and
then you overcome your greed your
aversion your delusion in regard to the
significance of those and that's that's
a subtle distinction that people would
wouldn't see so and it's the same with
you know um acknowledging that there are
Aesthetics and brahans who are realize
this world and Proclaim it that too is
of significance because if it wasn't
like that then what I even practicing
right so so so so to have that Faith
like yeah there are people who see these
things for themselves and based on that
actual knowledge that they have they are
capable of expounding that if you don't
have that then then then where's your
that then then then where's your
practice then either you want to become
a Buddha yourself which is again
overshooting the mark because that's not
quite necessary there already was a
Buddha who has taught the dharm so the
goal is not to become a Buddha just
become that's good enough basically yeah
and and connected with that there can
also be a view like um
that that the truth is sort of
like uh there are different truths let's put
uh there are different truths let's put
it that way like like you know the
the when people try to mix like all the
different religions and say like you
know they're all talking about the same
thing because it's yeah this is this is
the uh this I think this is sometimes
called like perennial philosophy which
is the overall term which says that
basically all spiritual or religious
traditions they spring from the same
source and they point to the same truth
now for many people that's pleasing to
hold that view but why is that because
in the end it doesn't actually really
matter what you do as long as it's half
religious or spiritual for lack of
better words you can't go wrong so that
that becomes a justification for a
massive lack of discernment because you
can just do this that and the other and
you think that if you just put it all on
top of one another it counts
and then you don't have to recognize the
fact that no there is right and
wrong there is there has to be some
distinction between like not not
everything that you do in the name of
spirituality can be considered right
like there are things that are taking
you away from from uh freedom from greed
diversion and delusion which is what the
Buddha described as spirituality yes not
uh just anything that that's uh you
might regard as less mundane that the
things that you're used to
so
um so that's that's that's the other
part yes so you need to um have a
recognition that not just that there is a
that not just that there is a
possibility
to understand things as it says that
there are atics and brahans who proclaim
the world after having understood it but
that um as Buddha said in one of those sutas
um as Buddha said in one of those sutas
he said like he came to this Aesthetics
and ask them oh is is there one
culmination or are there
many that's I think that's 11 he said
like um the there and he said if they were to
um the there and he said if they were to
answer rightly they would say there is
one culmination and then uh he asked if
is that culmination for one who is free
from greed a virin delusion or one who
is not free from those things and so
basically um setting forth that uh those
criteria that
um there has to be that distinction
basically between no not just anything that you
between no not just anything that you
would regarded Liberation counts it has
to be in terms of creed verion delusion
that would often not be
emphasized um in terms of like when
people talk about religious experiences
and stuff even in the context of
Buddhism MH um you know you might hear
them talking about all sorts of other
things except
you know how
much uh concern for the world and and
and desire in a verion has been
destroyed more like I had this these
magical insights and stuff that that I
didn't have before but you know what
that that part that
is that is kind of the the goalpost or
or the the thing that you should be
aiming for is not really being addressed
so then that's another form of view that
that could uh obstruct practice like
what is the freedom about in the first
place what is the goal
about yeah so people might actually
genuinely on account of having some
teaching or other have an initial sense
of relief but that but but there needs
to be a further discernment than that
because you know indulging in sensual
pleasure can also give relief but but
that is going in the wrong direction so
you cannot just say oh I feel more at
ease or I feel a sense that the pressure
has been therefore it's moving in the
right direction or delighting in being
as the Buddha said like there's there's
um there's different things so so then
there's Aesthetics who like even back in
the day they wouldn't be crudely
engaging in sensuality but they would be
getting gratification out of their views
and out of their their practices so as
we discussed before the discussion about
um virtue and observances
so
um all of that comes with within mundane
Right View like
having having um a direction of where
you're actually going
like not just anything that you start
with believing that that's what the Dum
is about you can take it for granted and
start practicing with it uh so
essentially that would be more of
a you would gain like 99% of the work is
to question the assumptions that you're
starting with it's not to just go with
those assumptions and then try to build
something on top of them essentially
with and that's what what uh but that's
more pleasant because like because one
finds a full sense of Safety and
Security on the level of views precisely
so that that's the right thing to do MH
so to so to say in the practice uh it's
it's that questioning of what what are
the views that I'm starting with do I am
I you know on some subtle level not
acknowledging the fact that there is
mother and father that there is action
that there are results of those actions
MH am I denying that for example even
the the one we're talking about now
like the that there are atics and
brahans who have realized that world
this world and the next well I've even
heard some people saying that you know
freedom from G version illusion is not
actually possible that you know because we we are
possible that you know because we we are
primates we're human primates like we we
have these animal sort of drives and so
there are things that we can't help to
like we can't help for example to have
sexual desire because uh we are
biologically wired to have those things
Bic or that uh so then they would
confuse that with oh so then freedom is
not possible basically but then they
would still be trying to practice the
dhama but now with like all sorts of
other views
that have nothing to do with it so
um those are basically all of those are
essentially ways of not taking
responsibility that's the fundamental
that's the common threat that runs
through that whole description in fact
there's another sutta where where the
Buddha was questioning groups of
Aesthetics and then um you know he was
saying like
um if someone holds to view that all
Pleasure and Pain that is experienced
right now is the result of what was done
in the
past um then would that be right view or
wrong View and then the Buddha question
tells Aesthetics and and they H that
view but yeah if if that's someone's
view that will again inhibit uh personal
responsibility and then it goes on to
say like if someone thinks that whatever
Pleasure and Pain they experience is the
result of a Creator God for example um
that's also in the end going to be
problematic because you see if someone
accepts that view then in the end you
would regard him I.E God as responsible
for what's happening and not yourself
and and and you cannot at the same time
hold the view that that you are
responsible for abandoning un wholesome
and developing wholesome and at the same
time say that all this is the result of
some being that is that that is
basically putting the strings behind the
scene that's a contradiction that that
cannot that's not
sustainable and you can also it it
doesn't even need to be God you could
have a belief the thing I just said um
that oh it's this biological hormones
and stuff that creates my actions yeah
all brain chemistry yeah it's not me
choosing to do these things it's
basically like the the biology by itself
is is H is making these motions so uh
that's that's just
a essentially the same thing you you you
you don't talk about God M but it it is
a belief that another like something
else is is doing the actions for you and
that would prevent you from from
actually developing yourself because all
of it as the Buddha said suffering is
born from Kama suffering is born from
action MH so then if you don't accept
that there is action in the first place
then you're basically covering up the
the the problem so as to kind of like
you have a bunch of dirt in a room and
instead of cleaning it up you just put a
big big tarp over it and then and try to
forget about it basically yeah but it is
you see to to some extent that might
still be pleasing to people because it
takes the it takes to some extent the
the the burden or the weight of their
own shoulders but the whole point is as
we discussed in earlier talk that um
that one will be incapable of freeing
oneself from suffering if one does not
fully take responsibility not just for
this or that action but for the fact
that one finds oneself in the world at
all that has got to be the starting
point and then you start to work from
within that situation see if you can
find a way out so that's again the thing
of authenticity that we were talking
about it's uh that uh recognition
that if you're not
free if you want to put it that way it's
it's your fault like nothing else
nothing in the world can be blamed for
you not being free from suffering
even like you
know if
it's the most trying circumstances like
you were born and or you you found the
dama too late and you already had you
know too many defilements or something
there's no such thing as that like you
always have a choice to give up greed
vision and delusion right now you might
not want to do it but there's always
something that you can be doing to be
closer and that's all you should be
concerned with like there is um anything
that I can do in that direction
basically uh if I just lament that you
know something else is imposing these
defilements on me and I can't overcome
them then there's there's nothing you
can do like my camera is too bad yeah
that's that's a that's a big one like
especially esally you know people cuz
you can see like this so this is the
mundane Right View and then it's talking
about there is action there is good and
bad action and then some some Buddhists
generally like trying to have that view
very much they would believe so much in
K that they would say well look I'm I
have been trying to practice for so many
years now and the reason why I'm not
able to achieve enlightenment is because
I have all this bad K from the past mm
and so like I need to stop practicing
focus on making Merit so then in the
future life I will be able to actually
uh reach ni and then funny thing is like
people don't realize but the The Janes
were saying exactly the same thing when
when they when they uh they were they
were saying the Buddha would ask them
like so why are you doing all these
these uh you know self mortification and
stuff and then they would say well
because we have so much bad K by doing
this stuff we wear away the results of
our bad actions and then the B asked
them so do you see do you have like
recollection of your past lives to know
that you actually did all that bad K and
then they say no we don't and so and
then and then in the end what they
answered was like well the view is
simply pleasing and agreeable to us so
what this with this aism is we find it
and then he also asked like do you see
I've worn away this much bad Comm and
there's still that that much to be worn
away and there was basically completely
puzzled yeah this is like the vipasana
movement their view of Saras as being
this accumulation of things that you
need to erode away through your
concentration yeah in general like if
you believe that the defs Ian I mean the
thing we often talk about like um when
you when you need to get rid of your
thoughts or you believe you need to get
rid of your thoughts in order to be at
peace you you essentially think that
these things that come by themselves are
responsible for your suffering like the
suffering is happening because of this
thing is is knocking at my door and I
can't like if it if it
comes basically it's it's it's that
thing's fault yeah so you can see that's
How Deep The View that this this not
taking mundane
Right View goes like just not taking
View goes like just not taking
responsibility for your own greed
version illusion even through supposedly
practicing the dhama like through
meditation and stuff so it's a that's
why I started by saying it's a much more
deeply rooted thing that people than
people realize so and
um like the
the if
you like you don't need to be worried
essentially about anything else like
what is my
view the view that I approach this whole
practice with
mhm that that should be your concern not
like I'll just uh oh it's because I
don't know this method or that method or
I haven't found out you know I haven't
studied enough sutas or or no it's what
are the assumptions what are the
attitudes with which you approach this
whole thing and then mhm re continuing
to review that but then that's that's
that's like you know when you have a
movie you don't want to be actually
knowing that you're watching a movie you
want to get absorbed in the movie so you
can enjoy the plot and that's exactly
the same thing like you don't if if if
you keep that kind of background
perspective that of questioning your
motivations and and attitudes while
you're doing the practice the whole
thing Bec is much more unpleasant than
many of the sort of releases and and the
you know
mundane pleasure pleasure that people
might get from the practice you can't
get it anymore because all that stuff
requires you not to be questioning
yourself MH it requires you to kind of
get into this hypnosis basically where
you where you don't question what you're
doing you're
just going in this direction and
wherever it takes you you blissing out
and that's it so mhm and the waiting go
yeah anticipating praying praying upon
something so it's it's so that attitude
undoing it's much more kind of
demanding it takes yeah it takes like a
it's like a dissonance like it's it's
not that it's going to be you know uh
agonizing pain the whole time mhm that
that you start practicing it's more like
a like you have this little sort of
noise there that that's not that's not
really what you want it because it's
going against the grain that's what the
Buddha me said the practice goes against
the grain
so it's also like you know undermining
the ground on which you are standing
exactly so the whole world is basically
to be put in question World which you
inhabit and feel secure in pleased with
and so on you might think is just about
you know running on top of that ground
mhm to where you think you should be
going but no it's about the fact that you know
but no it's about the fact that you know
undoing the ground that you're standing
on that's not a that's not a that that
that would be recognized as pleasant
when you have trained your mind before
that it's it's going to
be not really like you would have to use
your discernment to keep going like to
to motivate you to to keep going because
the mind in itself doesn't doesn't
really want to go in that direction yeah
I was thinking kind of about like you
can almost approach it with the view
that it's like this epic battle that you
kind of suit up for and you go and you
fight it and it's like this heroic you
know courageous moment but like it's
it's less
um it's not
so epic it I guess a good way of putting
it is like a good hero's journey Story
the hero does not want to be doing the
hero's journey that's when one good
thing to mention because when the Buddha
talked about the five Aggregates he
doesn't say or the defat in general he
doesn't say that it's it's like like you
said like you're in a battlefield and
you see the soldiers coming towards you
like you're going to fight them head on
he he gave a simile that it's it's like
a like a rich householder who would have
a a servant mhm who basically they would
the servant would come to him very nice
L very politely and start working for
him and then but from the very start the
that servant's goal was to kill the
householder so then while he was leaping
the you know or when he when he just
wasn't aware that servant was living in
his house M the entire time and then he
kills him yeah so the householder came
to trust the servants and then and then
after a long time it was called of guard
yeah and basically sted him with a knife
few times so so the the um all the
things that you have to overcome are
coming from that sort of indirect
direction that you actually have trust
in the the things that you that you
think are for your welfare they're
basically the things that that are right
there waiting to kill you so any sort of
pleasure you might be getting from the
practice if it hasn't given you the
right view you should be skeptical
because it is very likely that it is the
pleasure the pleasure of the trust in
that very thing that for now is nice for
now is is uh comfortable but
eventually it's going to stop you still
that's this Al about the five agregates
that the Buddha says that one is
devoured by the by by those agregates
yeah actually the that's how it get gets
actually the that's how it get gets
translated but I think the the it
actually means like I am itching with I
am itching with these with form itching
with feeling itching with the thing is
in in English that's not a really
doesn't really make sense but that's
kind of what it means so it's not um
it's coming like on that level like this
thing is itching it's like on you
basically it's not some sort of you know
enemy out there that's it's right there
in your personal sort of space that's
where the whole problem is not in not in
anything else that you may blame for you
know getting rid of
your managing your environment
essentially SRA has a play called No
Exit and the basically the premise is
these characters are in Hell and Hell is
like this very kind of mundane and
you're just stuck in a room with three
people and they the hell out of you
essentially and kind of it ends with
this culmination this dude knocking on
the door he's like let me out you know
give me the like chains in the fire and
the you know the torture chair is like
anything but this like subtle nagging
you know it's not bad enough that's the
the sort of uh discomfort of or the
disin of existence like like when you
recognize that
responsibility it's like
um it's it's it's something like that
it's not a it's not like you're carrying
a mountain I think that's that's what we
were discussing the other day it's not
like like the pain of carrying a lot of
of stu stuff it's more like you have a
bunch of pointy little rocks in your in
your foot in your shoe it's it's
something like that so it's
um the practice basically is is not
should not be expected to be
comfortable uh unless you you are
already far far like yeah Beyond
so that's another view like am I
expecting the practice to result in
pleasure as soon as possible mhm or do I
recognize that there is a problem here
that need needs to be fixed and it's not
necessarily going to be going to be you
know a nice ride right away obviously
eventually you want to be free from
suffering but you have to recognize like
anything uh in the beginning it's it's
always a grind so to say yeah yeah I
think that's very important like what
you say also like the things with
recognizing one's own attitude like link
to what you just said because if one
doesn't recognize that okay I'm actually
wanting to get rid of that so I'm acting
out of fion and craving like my whole
practice is based on that so everything
that I can recognize as peaceful or as
pleasant is actually toward within the
senses so it cannot result in anything
basically yeah and doesn't matter how
peaceful it is it is within the same the
same container so then that's why if it
is if it just comes easily to you kind
of at the same time or or parallel to
your lay life and your your possessions
and your worldly engagements and you
kind of have it side by side like that
that's a good indication that this other
thing is just coming basically within
the same taking place within those same
attitudes that you are used to because
it didn't require you to transform your
your mind your way of existing like just
imagine if you had a dog that was that
was wild and uh you know or a child that
was that was spoiled and and you know
behaving having bad bad behavior and
suddenly the next day it's it's like an
angel well you might be suspicious that
there's um you know
underlying it's not a it didn't
magically change like that so the same
thing with in mind if you have been you
know acting out of G verion delusion and
suddenly you find this pleasure and it's
really wonderful and you know all the
all the suffering is gone well you
should be skeptical about that
because so one should like should tell
himself like quite hard but like I don't
know what happiness is like I don't know
like I'm suffering and I don't know how
to me out
yeah the Buddha the Buddha said the the
whole world
sees the pleasant sight sounds smells St
taste touches and thoughts like
phenomena as pleasant and The Sensation
the the actual thing that's
Pleasant uh is seen as unpleasant by the
world which is the sensation of those
things and he says the noble ones are
the ones who understand that as the true
pleasure you have to understand like
whatever I regard as pleasure not like I
have to get rid of it because then we
get into the same thing we were
discussing before like you want to deny
the significance of everything but you
can't take it as the way to Enlighten it
you can't assume that if it's Pleasant
it's going to be us pleasure is going to
rise on its own mhm uh but it can't be
taken as a vehicle that's when that's
when um because you end up with all
sorts of of um
misconceptions like you know
uh meta for example meta practice like
you assume that you just generate this
Pleasant feeling these Pleasant feelings
and that's it like you're you're you're
already practicing you know the you're
you're on the way to Nana radiating
these Pleasant feelings all over the
place yeah and you never had to go
through any sort of training like you
just everything just fit together
magically like that so that's just too
good to be true basically